I've been spending a lot of time
أنا أقضي الكثير من الوقت
traveling around the world these days,
مسافرة حول العالم هذه الأيام
talking to groups of students and professionals,
متحدثة إلى مجموعات من الطلاب و المهنيين.
and everywhere I'm finding that I hear similar themes.
و في كل مكان أجد أني أسمع مواضيع متشابهة.
On the one hand, people say,
من جانب, الناس يقولون,
"The time for change is now."
"حان وقت التغيير."
They want to be part of it.
هم يُريدون أن يكونوا جزء منه.
They talk about wanting lives of purpose and greater meaning.
هم يتحدثون عن الرغبة في حياة ذات غاية ومعاني أعظم.
But on the other hand,
لكن على الجانب الآخر,
I hear people talking about fear,
أسمع الناس يتحدثون عن الخوف,
a sense of risk-aversion.
إحساس النفور من المخاطرة.
They say, "I really want to follow a life of purpose,
هم يقولون " أود حقا أن أتّبع حياة ذات غاية,
but I don't know where to start.
لكنّى لا أعرف من أين أبداء,
I don't want to disappoint my family or friends."
أنا لا أًريد أن أخيب أمل عائلتي أو أصدقائي."
I work in global poverty.
أنا أعمل في منظمة مكافحة الفقر العالمي.
And they say, "I want to work in global poverty,
و هم يقولون " أود أن أعمل في الفقر العالمي,
but what will it mean about my career?
لكن ماذا سيعني هذا بالنسبة لمهنتي؟
Will I be marginalized?
هل سأتزوج؟
Will I not make enough money?
ألن أجني قدر كافي من المال؟
Will I never get married or have children?"
ألن أتزوج أبدا أو أنجب أطفال؟"
And as a woman who didn't get married until I was a lot older --
و كإمراءة لم تتزوج حتي عمر متقدم --
and I'm glad I waited --
وأنا سعيدة أني انتظرت --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- and has no children,
-- وليس لي أطفال,
I look at these young people
أنظر لهؤلاء الشباب
and I say, "Your job is not to be perfect.
و أقول " ليس عملكم أن تكونوا مثاليين.
Your job is only to be human.
عملٌكم فقط أن تكونوا إنسانيين.
And nothing important happens in life
ولا شيْ مهم يحدث في الحياة
without a cost."
من غير ثمن."
These conversations really reflect what's happening
هذة المُحادثات تعكس حقاً ما يحدث
at the national and international level.
علي المستوى الوطني و الدولي.
Our leaders and ourselves
قادتُنا و أنفسنا
want everything,
نُريد كل شيئ.
but we don't talk about the costs.
لكننا لا نتحدث عن الثمن.
We don't talk about the sacrifice.
نحن لا نتحدث عن التضحية.
One of my favorite quotes from literature
إحدى الإقتباسات المفضًلة لدي من الأدب
was written by Tillie Olsen,
كتبَتها تيلي أولسن,
the great American writer from the South.
ألكاتبة الأمريكية العظيمة من الجنوب.
In a short story called "Oh Yes,"
في قصة قصيرة إسمها "أوو نعم,"
she talks about a white woman in the 1950s
تتحث عن أمراءة بيضاء في حقبة الخمسينيات
who has a daughter
كانت لها إبنة
who befriends a little African American girl,
صادقت فتاة صغيرة أمريكية من أصول أفريقية.
and she looks at her child with a sense of pride,
وهي تنظر لطفلتها بإعتزاز,
but she also wonders,
لكنها أيضا تتسائل,
what price will she pay?
ما الثمن الذي ستدفعه؟
"Better immersion
"ألأفضل الإنغماس
than to live untouched."
من العيش بمنأى."
But the real question is,
لكن السؤال الحقيقي هو,
what is the cost of not daring?
ما ثمن عدم الجرأة؟
What is the cost of not trying?
ما ثمن عدم المحاولة؟
I've been so privileged in my life
في حياتي كان لي إمتياز
to know extraordinary leaders
أن أتعرّف على قادة غير عاديين
who have chosen to live lives of immersion.
قرروا أن يحيوا حياة غامرة.
One woman I knew who was a fellow
تعرّفت على إمراءة كانت زميلة
at a program that I ran at the Rockefeller Foundation
في برنامج أدرته في مؤسسة روكفيلر
was named Ingrid Washinawatok.
كان إسمها إنغريد واشيناواتوك.
She was a leader of the Menominee tribe,
كانت قائدة قبيلة مينوميني,
a Native American peoples.
واحدة من شعوب أمريكا الأصليين.
And when we would gather as fellows,
و عندما كنا نجتمع كزملاء,
she would push us to think about
كانت تدفعنا لنُفكِّر في
how the elders in Native American culture
كيف كان الشيوخ في ثقافة الأمريكيين الأصليين
make decisions.
يتّخذون القرارات.
And she said they would literally visualize
وهي تقول أنهم حرفيّا يتخيلون
the faces of children
وجوه الأطفال
for seven generations into the future,
لسبعة أجيال في المستقبل,
looking at them from the Earth,
ناظرين إليهم من الأرض
and they would look at them, holding them as stewards
وهم ينظرون إليهم كحُكّام
for that future.
لذلك المستقبل.
Ingrid understood that we are connected to each other,
إنغريد أدركت أننا متصلون ببعض.
not only as human beings,
ليس فقط كبشر,
but to every living thing on the planet.
ولكن بأي شيئ حي على الكوكب.
And tragically, in 1999,
و بمأساوية, في العام 1999
when she was in Colombia
عندما كانت في كولمبيا
working with the U'wa people,
أعمل مع شعب الأووا,
focused on preserving their culture and language,
مُركِّزة على الحفاظ على ثقافتهم و لغتهم,
she and two colleagues were abducted
تم خطفها هي و زميلين
and tortured and killed by the FARC.
و تعذيبهم و قتلهم من قِبل القوات المسلحة الثورية لكولومبيا.
And whenever we would gather the fellows after that,
وكلّما اجتمعنا بعد ذلك كزُملاء,
we would leave a chair empty for her spirit.
كنّا نترك مقعداً خالياً لروحها.
And more than a decade later,
وبعد أكثر من عقد,
when I talk to NGO fellows,
عندما أتحدث لزملاء ألمنظّمات غير الحكومية,
whether in Trenton, New Jersey or the office of the White House,
سواء كان في ترنتون , نيوجيرزي أو مكتب البيت الأبيض,
and we talk about Ingrid,
ونتحدث عن إنغريد,
they all say that they're trying to integrate her wisdom
كلّهم يقولون أنهم يحاولون أن يدمجوا حِكمتها
and her spirit
و روحها
and really build on the unfulfilled work
و يبنوا فعلياً فوق العمل غير المكتمل
of her life's mission.
لمهمة حياتها.
And when we think about legacy,
وعندما نُفكر في ميراث,
I can think of no more powerful one,
لا أستطيع أن أُفكر واحد أقوى,
despite how short her life was.
على الرغم من أن حياتها كانت قصيرة.
And I've been touched by Cambodian women --
ولقد تأثرت بِنساء كمبوديات,
beautiful women,
نساء جميلات,
women who held the tradition of the classical dance in Cambodia.
نساء حملن تراث الرقص التقليدي في كمبوديا.
And I met them in the early '90s.
إلتقيت بهن في بداية التسعينيات.
In the 1970s, under the Pol Pot regime,
في السبعينيات,في ظل نظام بول بوت,
the Khmer Rouge killed over a million people,
قتل الخمير الحُمر أكثر من مليون شخص.
and they focused and targeted the elites and the intellectuals,
وقد ركّزوا على و استهدفوا الصفوة و المثقفين,
the artists, the dancers.
ألفنانيّن, ألراقصيّن.
And at the end of the war,
وفي نهاية الحرب,
there were only 30 of these classical dancers still living.
كان هنالك فقط 30 من هؤلاء الراقصين التقليديين على قيد الحياة.
And the women, who I was so privileged to meet
والنساء ألآئي كان لي إمتياز مقابلتهم
when there were three survivors,
عندما كان هنالك ثلاثة ناجين,
told these stories about lying in their cots
حكوا هذة القصص عن الإستلقاء في أكواخهم
in the refugee camps.
في معسكرات النازحين.
They said they would try so hard
قالوا أنهم كانوا يحاولون بجهد
to remember the fragments of the dance,
أن يتذكروا مقاطع الرقصة,
hoping that others were alive and doing the same.
آمليين أن يكون هنالك آخرون أحياء و يفعلون نفس الشيئ.
And one woman stood there with this perfect carriage,
و إمراءة وقفت هناك بهذا الحِمل المثالي,
her hands at her side,
يداها إلى جانبها,
and she talked about
و تحدّثت عن
the reunion of the 30 after the war
جمع شمل الـ 30 بعد الحرب
and how extraordinary it was.
وكيف أن ذلك كان إستثنائياً.
And these big tears fell down her face,
وسقطت تلك الدموع الغزيرة على وجهها,
but she never lifted her hands to move them.
لكنها مطلقاً لم ترفع يديها لتمسحها.
And the women decided that they would train
ولقد قررت النساء أنّهن سيُدرِّبن,
not the next generation of girls, because they had grown too old already,
ليس الجيل التالي من الفتيات,لأنهن كنّ قد كبرن,
but the next generation.
ولكن الجيل الذي يليه.
And I sat there in the studio
ولقد جلست هنالك في الأستديو,
watching these women clapping their hands --
أراقب هؤلاء النساء يُصفِقن بأيديهن --
beautiful rhythms --
إيقاعات جميلة --
as these little fairy pixies
بينما هذه الجنيات الصغيرات
were dancing around them,
يرقصن حولهن,
wearing these beautiful silk colors.
وهن يلبسن هذة الألوان الحريرية الجميلة.
And I thought, after all this atrocity,
ولقد فكّرت,بعد كل هذة الفظاعة,
this is how human beings really pray.
هذه هي الكيفية التي يصلي بها البشر فعلاً.
Because they're focused on honoring
لأنّهم مركزون على تكريم
what is most beautiful about our past
الشي الأجمل في ماضينا
and building it into
وبناءه في داخل
the promise of our future.
الوعد بمستقبلنا.
And what these women understood
وما فهِمنه هؤلاء النساء
is sometimes the most important things that we do
أنّه احياناً أهم الأشياء ألتي نفعلها
and that we spend our time on
والتي نقضي فيها وقتنا
are those things that we cannot measure.
هي تلك الأشياء ألتي لا نستطيع قياسها.
I also have been touched
لقد تأثرت أيضاً
by the dark side of power and leadership.
بالجانب المظلم للسُلطة والقيادة.
And I have learned that power,
ولقد تعلمت أنّ السُلطة,
particularly in its absolute form,
تحديداً في شكلها المطلق,
is an equal opportunity provider.
هي مُزوِّد لتكافُوء ألفرص.
In 1986, I moved to Rwanda,
في عام 1986, إنتقلت إلى رواندا,
and I worked with a very small group of Rwandan women
وعمِلت مع مجموعة صغيرة جداً من النساء الروانديات
to start that country's first microfinance bank.
لفتح مصرف للتمويلات الصغيرة
And one of the women was Agnes --
وإحدى هؤلاء النساء كانت آغنيس --
there on your extreme left --
هناك على أقصي يسارِكُم --
she was one of the first three
كانت واحدة من أول ثلاثة
women parliamentarians in Rwanda,
نساء برلمانيات في رواندا,
and her legacy should have been
وكان ينبغي ان يكون إرثها
to be one of the mothers of Rwanda.
أن تكون إحدى أمهات رواندا.
We built this institution based on social justice,
بنينا هذه المؤسسة على أساس العدالة الإجتماعية,
gender equity,
ألمساواة بين الجنسين,
this idea of empowering women.
فكرة تمكين النساء.
But Agnes cared more about the trappings of power
ولكن آغنيس في النهاية إهتمّت بزخارف السُلطة
than she did principle at the end.
أكثر من المبدأ.
And though she had been part of building a liberal party,
وعلى الرغم من أنها كانت جزء من إنشاء حِزب لبرالي,
a political party
حِزب سياسي,
that was focused on diversity and tolerance,
والذي ركّز علي التنوع و التسامح.
about three months before the genocide, she switched parties
قبل ثلاثة أشهر من الإبادة الجماعية, تركت حِزبها
and joined the extremist party, Hutu Power,
وأنضمت للحِزب الاكثر تطرفاً, قوة الهوتو,
and she became the Minister of Justice
وأصبحت وزيرة العدل
under the genocide regime
في ظل نظام الإبادة الجماعية
and was known for inciting men to kill faster
وعُرِفت بتحريض الرجال للقتل بطريقة أسرع
and stop behaving like women.
والتوقف عن التصرف كـ نساء.
She was convicted
تمّت إدانتها
of category one crimes of genocide.
بجرائم الإبادة الجماعية من الدرجة الأولى.
And I would visit her in the prisons,
ولقد زُرتها في السجن
sitting side-by-side, knees touching,
وجلسنا جنباً إلى جنب, رُكبنا متلامسة,
and I would have to admit to myself
ولقد إعترفْت لنفسي
that monsters exist in all of us,
بأن الوحوش موجودة في داخلنا كلّنا,
but that maybe it's not monsters so much,
لكن ذلك قد يكون ليس الوحوش بدرجة كبيرة,
but the broken parts of ourselves,
لكن الأجزاء المكسورة في أنفسنا,
sadnesses, secret shame,
أحزان,عار سِرِّي,
and that ultimately it's easy for demagogues
وأنه في نهاية المطاف من السهل على المنظرين الديماغوجيون
to prey on those parts,
أن يفترسوا تلك الأجزاء,
those fragments, if you will,
تلك الشظايا,
and to make us look at other beings, human beings,
و يجعلوننا ننظر للكائنات الاُخرى, البشر,
as lesser than ourselves --
كأنّهم أقل مِنّا --
and in the extreme, to do terrible things.
و في الحد الأقصى, أن نعمل أشياء فظيعة.
And there is no group
وليس هنالك مجموعة
more vulnerable to those kinds of manipulations
عُرضة لتلك الأنواع من التلاعب
than young men.
أكثر من الشباب.
I've heard it said that the most dangerous animal on the planet
سمِعت قولاً أن أخطر الحيوانات على الأرض
is the adolescent male.
هو الذَّكَر اليافع.
And so in a gathering
ولِذلك ففي التجمعات
where we're focused on women,
حيث نركِّز على النساء,
while it is so critical that we invest in our girls
حينما يكون من الجوهري جدا أن نستثمر في فتياتنا
and we even the playing field
ونوازن الملعب
and we find ways to honor them,
ونجد طُرق لِتكريمهم,
we have to remember that the girls and the women
علينا أن نتذكّر أن الفتيات والنساء
are most isolated and violated
هن أكثر عٌزلةً وانتهاكاً
and victimized and made invisible
و ضحيةً وإخفاءاً
in those very societies
تحديداً في تلك المجتمعات
where our men and our boys
التي فيها رجالنا و اولادنا
feel disempowered,
يشعرون بأنهم مستضعفون,
unable to provide.
غير قادرين على العطاء.
And that, when they sit on those street corners
وذلك عندما يجلسون في زوايا الشوارع
and all they can think of in the future
وكل ما يستطيعون التفكير فيه في المستقبل
is no job, no education,
هو عدم العمل ,عدم التعليم,
no possibility,
عدم الإمكانية,
well then it's easy to understand
عندئذ من السهل أن نفهم
how the greatest source of status
كيف أن المصدر الأعظم للهيبة
can come from a uniform
يمكن أن يأتي من زي نظامي
and a gun.
و بندقية.
Sometimes very small investments
أحياناً إستثمارات صغيرة جداً
can release enormous, infinite potential
يُمكن أن تطلق إمكانيات هائلة لا نهائية
that exists in all of us.
موجودة في داخلنا.
One of the Acumen Fund fellows at my organization,
أحد زملاء صندوق الفطنة في مؤسستي,
Suraj Sudhakar,
سراج سودهاكر,
has what we call moral imagination --
لديه ما نسمية الخيال الأخلاقي --
the ability to put yourself in another person's shoes
المقدِرة على أن تضع نفسك في مكان شخص آخر
and lead from that perspective.
و تقود من ذلك المنظور.
And he's been working with this young group of men
ولقد ظل يعمل مع تلك المجموعة الصغيرة من الرجال
who come from the largest slum in the world, Kibera.
ألذين يأتون من أكبر حي فقير في العالم, كيبيرا.
And they're incredible guys.
وهم اشخاص مُذهلون.
And together they started a book club
ومعاً بدءوا نادي للكتاب
for a hundred people in the slums,
لِمئة شخص في الأحياء الفقيرة,
and they're reading many TED authors and liking it.
وهم يقرءون الكثير من مؤلفات TED و يُحبونها.
And then they created a business plan competition.
وبعد ذلك كونوا منافسة خُطة عمل.
Then they decided that they would do TEDx's.
بعد ذلك قرروا أنهم سيقومون بعمل TEDx's.
And I have learned so much
ولقد تعلمت كثيراً جداً
from Chris and Kevin
من كريس و كيفن
and Alex and Herbert
وألكس و هربرت
and all of these young men.
وكل هؤلاء الشباب.
Alex, in some ways, said it best.
ألكس قالها بأفضل طريقة
He said, "We used to feel like nobodies,
قال,"كنا نشعر كأننا نكِرات,
but now we feel like somebodies."
لكن الأن نشعر كأننا أشخاص ما."
And I think we have it all wrong
وأعتقد أننا مخطئون تماماً
when we think that income is the link.
عندما نعتقد أن الدخل هو الرابِط.
What we really yearn for as human beings
ما نتوق اليه فعليناً نحن كبشر
is to be visible to each other.
هو أن نكون مرئيين لبعضنا البعض.
And the reason these young guys
ولقد أخبرني هؤلاء الشباب
told me that they're doing these TEDx's
أن السبب وراء قيامهم بتلك الـ TEDx's
is because they were sick and tired
أنهم تعبوا و ملّلوا
of the only workshops coming to the slums
مِن وِرَش العمل الوحيدة التي تأتي للحي الفقير
being those workshops focused on HIV,
والتي تُركِّز على الأيدز,
or at best, microfinance.
أو في أحسن الأحوال, ألتمويلات الصغيرة.
And they wanted to celebrate
وهم يٌريدون أن يحتفلوا
what's beautiful about Kibera and Mathare --
بما هو جميل في كيبيرا و ماثاري --
the photojournalists and the creatives,
ألمصورون الصحفيون و المبدعون,
the graffiti artists, the teachers and the entrepreneurs.
فنّاني الكتابة على الجدران, ألمعلمين والروّاد.
And they're doing it.
وهم يفعلون ذلك.
And my hat's off to you in Kibera.
أرفع قُبّعتي تحية لكم في كيبيرا.
My own work focuses
عملي الخاص يُركّز
on making philanthropy more effective
على جعل الاحسان أكثر فعالية
and capitalism more inclusive.
والرأسمالية أكثر شمولاً.
At Acumen Fund, we take philanthropic resources
في صندوق الفطنة, نأخذ الموارد الخيرية
and we invest what we call patient capital --
و نستثمر ما نسميه رأس المال الصبور --
money that will invest in entrepreneurs who see the poor
ألمال الذي سوف يستثمر في المشاريع التي ترى الفقراء,
not as passive recipients of charity,
ليس كمتلقيّن سلبيّن للصدقة,
but as full-bodied agents of change
ولكن كوكلاء مكتملين للتغيير
who want to solve their own problems
يريدون أن يعالجوا مشاكلهم الخاصة
and make their own decisions.
و يتخذون قراراتهم الخاصة.
We leave our money for 10 to 15 years,
نترُك مالنا لمدة 10 إلى 15 سنة,
and when we get it back, we invest in other innovations
وعندما نسترجِعها,نستثمر في إختراعات اُخرى
that focus on change.
تُركِّز على التغيير.
I know it works.
أنا أعلم أنّها ناجحة.
We've invested more than 50 million dollars in 50 companies,
لقد إستثمرنا أكثر من 50 مليون دولار في 50 شركة.
and those companies have brought another 200 million dollars
كل تلك الشركات جلبت 200 مليون دولار اُخرى
into these forgotten markets.
إلى تلك الأسواق المنسية.
This year alone, they've delivered 40 million services
في هذة السنة فقط,قدّمت 40 مليون خدمة
like maternal health care and housing,
مثل الرعاية الصحية للاُمّهات و الإسكان,
emergency services, solar energy,
خدمات الطوارئ, ألطاقة الشمسية,
so that people can have more dignity
بحيث يمكن أن يكون للناس المزيد من الكرامة
in solving their problems.
في حل مشاكلهم.
Patient capital is uncomfortable
رأس المال الصبور غير مريح
for people searching for simple solutions,
للناس الباحثين عن الحلول البسيطة,
easy categories,
الفِئات السهلة,
because we don't see profit as a blunt instrument.
لأننا لا نرى الرِبح كأداة مُتبلِدة.
But we find those entrepreneurs
ولكننا نجد المشاريع
who put people and the planet
التي تضع الناس و الكوكب
before profit.
قبل الرِبح.
And ultimately, we want to be part of a movement
وفي نهاية المطاف, نحن نود أن نكون جزء من حركة
that is about measuring impact,
هي عن قياس التأثير,
measuring what is most important to us.
قياس ما هو أهم بالنسبة لنا.
And my dream is we'll have a world one day
و حِلمي أن يكون لنا في يوم ما عالم
where we don't just honor those who take money
حيث لا نُكرِّم فقط الذين يأخذون المال
and make more money from it,
و يصنعون منه المزيد من المال,
but we find those individuals who take our resources
لكن نجد اولئك الأفراد الذين يأخذون مواردنا
and convert it into changing the world
و يحولونها لتغيير العالم
in the most positive ways.
بأكثر الطرق إيجابية.
And it's only when we honor them
وفقط عندما نُكرِّمهم
and celebrate them and give them status
و نحتفي بهم و نعطيهم مكانة
that the world will really change.
عندها سيتغير العالم فعلا.
Last May I had this extraordinary 24-hour period
في مايو الماضي كانت لي فترة الـ 24 ساعة غير الإعتيادية هذة
where I saw two visions of the world
حيث رأيت وجهتي نظر للعالم
living side-by-side --
تعيشان جنباً إلى جنب
one based on violence
واحدة موئسَّسة على العنف
and the other on transcendence.
والاُخرى على التعالي.
I happened to be in Lahore, Pakistan
حدث أن كنت في لاهور, باكستان
on the day that two mosques were attacked
في اليوم الذي تعرض فيه مسجدين للهجوم
by suicide bombers.
من جانب مُفجِّرين إنتحاريين.
And the reason these mosques were attacked
والسبب وراء الهجوم علي هذه المساجد
is because the people praying inside
هو أن الناس الذين يُصلّون داخلها
were from a particular sect of Islam
كانوا من طائفة معينة في الإسلام
who fundamentalists don't believe are fully Muslim.
يعتقد الاُصوليون أنهم ليسوا مسلمين كاملين.
And not only did those suicide bombers
وليس فقط أن اولئك المُفجِّرون الإنتحاريون
take a hundred lives,
قتلوا مئات الأرواح,
but they did more,
لكنهم فعلوا أكثر من ذلك,
because they created more hatred, more rage, more fear
لأنهم خلقوا المزيد من الكراهية, ألمزيد من الغضب, ألمزيد من الخوف
and certainly despair.
وبِلا شك اليأس.
But less than 24 hours,
لكن في أقل من 24 ساعة,
I was 13 miles away from those mosques,
كنت على بعد 13 ميل من تلك المساجد,
visiting one of our Acumen investees,
أزور أحد مستثمري الصندوق,
an incredible man, Jawad Aslam,
رجل غير عادي, جواد أسلم,
who dares to live a life of immersion.
ألذي تجراء أن يعيش حياة غامرة.
Born and raised in Baltimore,
وُلد و نشأ في بلتيمور,
he studied real estate, worked in commercial real estate,
درس العقارات, عمل في العقارات التجارية,
and after 9/11 decided he was going to Pakistan to make a difference.
وبعد 11/9 قرر أن يذهب الى باكستان ليصنع فارِقاً.
For two years, he hardly made any money, a tiny stipend,
لِعامين, جنى القليل من المال, راتب صغير جدا,
but he apprenticed with this incredible housing developer
لكِنّه تدرب مع مُطوِّر مساكن غير عادي
named Tasneem Saddiqui.
يدعى تسنيم صادقي.
And he had a dream that he would build a housing community
وكان له حلم أن يبني مجتمع إسكان
on this barren piece of land
فوق قطعة الأرض القاحِلة هذة
using patient capital,
بإستخدام رأس المال الصبور,
but he continued to pay a price.
لكنّه استمر في دفع الثمن.
He stood on moral ground
وقف علي أرضية اخلاقية
and refused to pay bribes.
ورفض أن يدفع رشاوي.
It took almost two years just to register the land.
إستغرق الأمر حوالي العامين لتسجيل الأرض فقط.
But I saw how the level of moral standard can rise
لكنّي رأيت كيف أن مُستوى المعيار الأخلاقي يمكن أن يرتفِع
from one person's action.
من تصرُّف شخص واحد.
Today, 2,000 people live in 300 houses
أليوم, 2000 شخص يعيشون في 300 منزل
in this beautiful community.
في هذا المجتمع الجميل.
And there's schools and clinics and shops.
وهنالك مدارس و عيادات و متاجر.
But there's only one mosque.
لكن هنالك مسجد واحد فقط.
And so I asked Jawad,
فسئلت جواد,
"How do you guys navigate? This is a really diverse community.
"كيف تُديرون يا شباب؟ هذا حقاً مجتمع متنوع.
Who gets to use the mosque on Fridays?"
من يستعمل المسجد في أيام الجُمعة؟"
He said, "Long story.
قال, "قِصة طويلة.
It was hard, it was a difficult road,
كان ذلك شاقاً, كان طريقاً صعباً,
but ultimately the leaders of the community came together,
لكن في نهاية المطاف جاء قادة المجتمع معاً,
realizing we only have each other.
مُدرِكين أن ليس لنا إلا بعضنا البعض.
And we decided that we would elect
و قررنا أننا سننتخِب
the three most respected imams,
الأئِمّة الثلاثة الأكثر إحتراماً,
and those imams would take turns,
واُؤلئِك الأئِمة سيتبادلون,
they would rotate who would say Friday prayer.
سيتناوبون على خطبة صلاة الجُمعة.
But the whole community,
لكن كل المجتمع,
all the different sects, including Shi'a and Sunni,
كل الطوائف المختلفة, بما فيهم الشيّعة و السنّة,
would sit together and pray."
سيجلسون معاً و يُصلّون.
We need that kind of moral leadership and courage
نحن نحتاج لذلك النوع من القيادة الأخلاقية و الشجاعة
in our worlds.
في عوالِمنا.
We face huge issues as a world --
نحن نواجه مواضيع ضخمة في عالمنا --
the financial crisis,
الأزمة المالية,
global warming
الإحتِرار العالمي
and this growing sense of fear and otherness.
وهذا الشعور المتنامي بالخوف والإختلاف.
And every day we have a choice.
وكل يوم لدينا خيار.
We can take the easier road,
يمكننا أن نأخذ الطريق الأسهل
the more cynical road,
الطريق الأكثر سُخرٍية,
which is a road based on
وهو طريق مؤسس أحيانا على
sometimes dreams of a past that never really was,
أحلام عن ماضي مطلقاً لم يكن,
a fear of each other,
خوف من بعضنا البعض,
distancing and blame.
إبعاد و لوم,
Or we can take the much more difficult path
أويُمكننا أن نأخذ الطريق الأصعب
of transformation, transcendence,
من التحول, التسامي
compassion and love,
الشفقة و الحب,
but also accountability and justice.
ولكن أيضا المٌسائلة و العدالة.
I had the great honor
كان لي عظيم الشرف
of working with the child psychologist Dr. Robert Coles,
أن أعمل مع طبيب الأطفال النفسي د. روبرت كوليس
who stood up for change
ألذي وقف من أجل التغيير
during the Civil Rights movement in the United States.
أثناء حركة الحقوق المدنية في الولايات المتحدة.
And he tells this incredible story
وهو يروي هذه القصة الرائعة
about working with a little six-year-old girl named Ruby Bridges,
عن عمله مع فتاة صغيرة ذات ستة أعوام إسمها روبي بريدجز,
the first child to desegregate schools in the South --
أوّل طِفلة في إلغاء ألفصل العنصري في المدارس في الجنوب --
in this case, New Orleans.
في نيواورليانز.
And he said that every day
وقد قال انّ كل يوم
this six-year-old, dressed in her beautiful dress,
هذة الفتاة ذات الستة أعوام, مرتدية فُستانها الجميل,
would walk with real grace
تسير بِشرف حقيقي
through a phalanx of white people
خلال كتيبة من الناس البيض
screaming angrily, calling her a monster,
يصرخون بِغضب, منادينها بالوحش,
threatening to poison her --
مُهددين بتسميمها --
distorted faces.
وجوه مشوّهة.
And every day he would watch her,
وكل يوم كان يراقبها,
and it looked like she was talking to the people.
وكان يبدو كأنها تتحدث إلي الناس.
And he would say, "Ruby, what are you saying?"
وكان يسئلها, "روبي, ماذا تقولين؟"
And she'd say, "I'm not talking."
وكانت تقول, "أنا لا أتكلم."
And finally he said, "Ruby, I see that you're talking.
واخيرا قال, "روبي أرى أنك تتحدثين.
What are you saying?"
ماذا تقولين؟"
And she said, "Dr. Coles, I am not talking;
فقالت, "د. كلوس, أنا لا أتكلم,
I'm praying."
أنا اُصلًي"
And he said, "Well, what are you praying?"
فقال, " حسنا بماذا تُصلّين؟"
And she said, "I'm praying, 'Father, forgive them,
فقالت, "أنا اُصلّي, يا رب أغفر لهم
for they know not what they are doing.'"
لأنّهم لا يعرفون ما يفعلون؟"
At age six,
في عُمر السادسة,
this child was living a life of immersion,
كانت هذة الطفلة تعيش حياة غامرة,
and her family paid a price for it.
وعائِلتها دفعت ثمن ذلك.
But she became part of history
لكنها أصبحت جزء من التاريخ
and opened up this idea
وأفتتحت هذه الفكرة
that all of us should have access to education.
بأننا كُلّنا يجب أن نحصل على فرصة في التعليم.
My final story is about a young, beautiful man
قصتي الأخيرة عن شاب جميل
named Josephat Byaruhanga,
يٌدعى جوزيفات بيروهانغا
who was another Acumen Fund fellow,
والذي كان أحد زُملاء صندوق الفِطنة
who hails from Uganda, a farming community.
والذي عاش في يوغندا, مجتمع زراعي.
And we placed him in a company in Western Kenya,
ولقد وضعناه في شركة في غرب كينيا.
just 200 miles away.
فقط علي بعد 200 ميل.
And he said to me at the end of his year,
وقد قال لي في نهاية العام,
"Jacqueline, it was so humbling,
جاكلين, لقد كان ذلك يدعو للتواضع بِشدّة,
because I thought as a farmer and as an African
لأنني أعتقدت كمزارع و كأفريقي
I would understand how to transcend culture.
أنني سأفهم كيف أتجاوز الثقافة.
But especially when I was talking to the African women,
لكن تحديداً عندما كنت أتحدث للنساء الافريقيات,
I sometimes made these mistakes --
أحياناً أرتكب هذه ألاخطاء --
it was so hard for me to learn how to listen."
كان صعبا علي جداً أن أتعلم كيف اُنصِت؟"
And he said, "So I conclude that, in many ways,
وقال, "لذلك أستنتجت, بطرق متعددة,
leadership is like a panicle of rice.
أن القيادة كسُنبلة الأرُز.
Because at the height of the season,
لأنها في قمة الموسم,
at the height of its powers,
في قمة قوتها,
it's beautiful, it's green, it nourishes the world,
جمالها,خضرتها,هي تغذي العالم,
it reaches to the heavens."
هي تصل الى السماء."
And he said, "But right before the harvest,
وقال, "لكن تماما قبل الحصاد,
it bends over
تنحني
with great gratitude and humility
بعرفان عظيم و تواضع
to touch the earth from where it came."
لتلمس الأرض من حيث أتت هي."
We need leaders.
نحن نحتاج لقادة.
We ourselves need to lead
نحن أنفسنا نحتاج أن نقود
from a place that has the audacity
من مكان فيه الجرأة
to believe we can, ourselves,
لأن نؤمِن أن بامكاننا نحن
extend the fundamental assumption
ان نوسع الافتراض الاساس
that all men are created equal
بأن كل الرجال خُلِقوا مساويين
to every man, woman and child on this planet.
لكل رجل,امراءة و طفل على هذا الكوكب.
And we need to have the humility to recognize
ونحتاج أن يكون عندنا التواضع لنعترف
that we cannot do it alone.
أننا لايمكن أن نفعلها لوحدنا.
Robert Kennedy once said
روبرت كينيدي قال ذات مرة
that "few of us have the greatness to bend history itself,
"ألقليل منّا لدية العظمة لتغير مسار التاريخ نفسه,
but each of us can work
ولكن كل منّا يستطيع أن يعمل
to change a small portion of events."
لتغيير جزء صغير من الأحداث.
And it is in the total of all those acts
وإنه في مجموع كل تلك الأفعال
that the history of this generation will be written.
سيُكتب تاريخ هذا الجيل."
Our lives are so short,
حياتنا قصيرة جداً,
and our time on this planet
ووقتنا في هذا الكوكب
is so precious,
ثمين جداً,
and all we have is each other.
وكل ما لدينا هو بعضنا البعض.
So may each of you
فهلّلا كل واحد منكم
live lives of immersion.
عاش حياة غامرة
They won't necessarily be easy lives,
ليس من الضروري أن تكون حياة سهلة,
but in the end, it is all that will sustain us.
ولكن في النهاية,هي كل الذي سيُبقينا.
Thank you.
شُكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)